Guide to the Records of UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention Studies (CAPS) AR.2005.15
University of California, San Francisco Archives & Special Collections
UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention Studies (CAPS) records
1984-2004
University of California, San Francisco Archives & Special Collections
University of California, San Francisco. Center for AIDS Prevention Studies
AR.2005.15
2.9 Linear Feet (2 cartons, 1 box)
The UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention Studies (CAPS) was established in 1986 to train scientists and stimulate new research projects that impact the practice, theory, and policy of HIV/AIDS prevention and keep pace with the changing epidemic. The CAPS records include reports, meeting and conference materials, correspondence, grant applications, committee and research project materials, and clippings and publications, dated 1984-2004.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. The UCSF Archives and Special Collections policy places access restrictions on material with privacy issues for a specific time period from the date of creation. Restrictions are noted at the folder level. This collection will be reviewed for sensitive content upon request. Contact the UCSF Archivist for information on access to restricted material.
Separated Materials
Selected publications from the collection have been transferred to the AIDS History Book Collection of the UCSF Archives and Special Collections. They have been individually cataloged and are available to researchers in the reading room.
Acquisition Information
This collection was transferred to the UCSF Archives and Special Collections by the UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention Studies in 2006.
Additions
No future additions are expected.
Related Collections
The collection is part of the AIDS History Project. Learn more about the project and related collections by contacting the UCSF Archivist or visiting www.library.ucsf.edu/archives/aids.
Organizational History
The UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention Studies (CAPS) was established in 1986 to educate scientists and stimulate new research projects that impact the practice, theory, and policy of HIV/AIDS prevention and keep pace with the changing epidemic. CAPS at first focused on the prevalence of HIV/AIDS and risk behaviors. A grant from the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH) helped the center grow and begin training medical, social, and behavioral scientists. The scope of CAPS has evolved over the decades to include global projects, the development of prevention interventions, and collaborative work among researchers in fields including biomedicine, psychology, epidemiology, behavioral science, policy, clinical medicine, and other disciplines. Many CAPS activities focus on HIV prevention and disparity reduction in ethnic minority communities and people of color and the center's training and educational programs encourage diversity in science. Major initiatives within CAPS have included the Technology and Information Exchange (TIE) Core and the Traineeships in AIDS Prevention Studies (TAPS) fellowship program. Prominent leaders within CAPS have included Thomas Coates, PhD, Cynthia A. Gomez, PhD, Stephen (Steve) Morin, PhD, Susan M. Kegeles, PhD, Marguerita Lightfoot, PhD, and others.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes material related to various CAPS, university, San Francisco Bay Area, and national HIV/AIDS research projects and prevention initiatives. Files include reports, meeting and conference materials, correspondence, grant applications, committee and research project materials, and clippings and publications. Some audiovisual and graphic material is also included (one audio cassette tape and slides). Files of Thomas Coates, PhD and Cynthia A. Gomez, PhD are included as well material regarding ACT UP San Francisco, AIDS Research Institute, CDC, GLBT organizations, and other associations and organizations.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged by subject-headed folders. Original folder arrangement and titles have been maintained with minimal intervention by the archivist.
AIDS (Disease); HIV infections--Prevention; University of California, San Francisco. Center for AIDS Prevention Studies
- Thomas Coates files, 1984-1993 (Carton 1, Folders 1-3)
  Scope and Contents
  Thomas Coates, PhD, co-founded CAPS in 1986 and directed it from 1991 to 2003. Files include AIDS-related grant applications, study questionnaires and interview protocols, and related material, including correspondence and grant material from Stephen (Steve) Morin and Stephen Hulley.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Material includes restricted personal information. Contact the UCSF Archivist for information on access to restricted files.
- Cynthia A. Gomez files, 1991-2004 (Carton 1, Folders 4-19)
  Biographical Information
  Cynthia A. Gomez, PhD, served as co-director of CAPS. Her work focuses primarily on gender, culture and sexual health, and the translation of science to community practice. She was appointed to the Presidential Advisory Committee on HIV/AIDS during the Clinton and Bush Administrations and served on the CDC's HIV and STD Advisory Council, NIDA's National Hispanic Science Network, and as a member of the Board of Trustees of the National AIDS Fund.
  Material includes restricted personal information (noted at the folder level). Contact the UCSF Archivist for information on access to restricted files.
  - Correspondence and conference materials, 1991-2004 (Carton 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript and congressional bill reviews, 1992-1997 (Carton 1, Folder 5)
  - PSG Computer Users Steering Committee, 2003-2004 (Carton 1, Folder 6)
  - Technology and Information Exchange (TIE) Core, 1991-1994 (Carton 1, Folder 7)
  - American Public Health Association Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Caucus of Public Health Workers, 1993-1995 (Carton 1, Folder 8)
  - American Psychological Association, Society for the Psychological Study of Lesbian, Gay and Bisexual Issues, Division 44, 1993-1998 (Carton 1, Folders 9-10)
  - Chancellor's Advisory Committee on Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual and Transgender (GLBT) Issues, 2004 (Carton 1, Folder 11)
  - Center for Women Policy Studies and Virucide/Microbicide Working Group, 1993-1994 (Carton 1, Folder 12)
  - Minority High School Research Apprentice Program, 1991-1992 (Carton 1, Folder 13)
  - UCSF AIDS Research Institute, 1997-1998 (Carton 1, Folder 14)
  - Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and Kaiser Foundation HIV/STD Behavioral Surveillance Workgroup and Workshop, 1995-1999 (Carton 1, Folder 15)
  - San Quentin Prison Project, 1991-1996 (Carton 1, Folder 16)
  - The Tarzana Project: An HIV Prevention Intervention for Latinas grant application, 1996 (Carton 1, Folder 17)
  - HIV Prevention Policy: The Role of Community Planning Groups grant application, 1999 (Carton 1, Folder 18)
  - HIV Infection and Related Risk in Homosexually Active Women grant application and related material, 1992 (Carton 1, Folder 19)
- Slides - Behavior Change and Prevention of Sexual Transmission of HIV presentation by Stephen F. Morin, circa 1988 (Carton 1, Folder 20)
- National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA) Hispanic Initiative on Drug Abuse and AIDS Research and Technology Transfer, 1993-1997 (Carton 1, Folders 21-26)
- AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power (ACT UP) San Francisco and HIV/AIDS denial, 1990-2004 (Carton 2, Folders 1-3)
  Files include correspondence and mailings, ephemera, newspaper clippings and publications, and audiovisual material (one audio cassette tape). The bulk of the material relates to ACT UP San Francisco's activism and HIV/AIDS denialism and the response of CAPS and other UCSF and San Francisco organizations.
- Michael Petrelis clippings and request for information materials, 1999-2002 (Carton 2, Folder 4)
- Willie Lewis Brown, Jr. Mayor's Summit on AIDS and HIV, 1997-1999 (Carton 2, Folder 5)
- Presidential Advisory Council on HIV/AIDS, 2000 (Carton 2, Folder 6)
- HIV Prevention Planning Council (HPPC) meetings, reports, and related material, 1994-1999 (Carton 2, Folders 7-9)
- HIV Prevention: Looking Back, Looking Ahead - Prevention Science Committee Briefing Book, 1994 (Carton 2, Folder 10)
- The San Francisco Department of Public Health and AIDS Research Institute/UCSF Response to the Updated Estimates of HIV Infection in San Francisco, 2000 (Carton 2, Folder 11)
- Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Advisory Committee on HIV and STD Prevention meetings and reports, 1995-1999 (Carton 2, Folder 12)
- Universitywide AIDS Research Program (UARP) grants, reports,and related material, 2001-2004 (Carton 2, Folder 13)
- Universitywide AIDS Research Program (UARP) Universitywide Task Force on AIDS booklets, 2001-2002 (Carton 2, Folders 14-15)
- Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) Summary of the Surveillance Branch Risk Consultation, 2001-2002 (Carton 2, Folder 16)
- AIDS and Mental Health: Policy, Administration, Treatment - papers from UCSF AIDS Clinical Research Center conference, 1985 (Carton 2, Folder 17)
- American Psychological Association Conference Program Guide - Technical Assistance Conference on Behavioral Science and HIV Prevention Community Planning, 1996 (Carton 2, Folder 18)
- American Psychological Association Behavioral Scientist Manual - Behavioral and Social Science Consultation with Three HIV Prevention Community Planning Groups Conference, 1996 (Box 1, Folders 1-2)
- AIDSCAP Behavioral Research Unit (BRU) Technical Working Group meeting workbook, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Formative Behavioral Intervention Research on the Prevention of Sexual Transmission of HIV by HIV-Seropositive Men - Qualitative Interviewing Skills Training Workshop manual, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ARI News - UCSF AIDS Research Institute newsletter, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- CAPS News and other UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention Studies publications, 1994-2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Publications and ephemera related to sexually transmitted diseases and HIV/AIDS, 1991-2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)